{"tossups": [{"question": "While deployed to Fort Bliss, this man\u2019s wife and children tragically died in a fire in San Francisco. Charles Stanton, this man\u2019s personal aide, recorded him as saying \u201cLafayette, we are here\u201d during a visit to Lafayette\u2019s tomb in Paris. This man was allowed to design his own insignia, choosing four gold stars, after being promoted to General of the Armies. For ten points, name this commander of the American Expeditionary Forces during World War I, a general nicknamed \u201cBlack Jack.\u201d", "answer": "John J.<b> Pershing</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This person created a polar area diagram divided into months, known as the \u201cRose\u201d diagram. The run-down facilities at Selimiye prompted this person to work with Isambard Brunel to create Renkioi, a facility that lessened mortality rates by 90%. At this person\u2019s request, Scutari hospital was investigated by the Sanitary Commission. This person\u2019s treatment of wounded soldiers led her to be known as the\u201cLady with the Lamp.\u201d For ten points, name this nurse active in the Crimean War.", "answer": "Florence<b> Nightingale</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This man issued the Code of the Rayas to improve the plight of Christians working on Sipahi farms. After forming the \u201cUnholy Alliance\u201d with Francis I, this man sent the corsair Hayreddin Barbarossa to patrol European waters. This man worked with Ebussuud Effendi in order to reconcile the Kanun code with Sha\u2019ria, earning the title Lawgiver. For ten points, identify this longest reigning Ottoman sultan who brought the empire to its territorial height.", "answer": "<b> Suleiman the Magnificent</b> (accept<b> Suleiman I</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "During the debates over this agreement, Henry S. Foote drew a pistol on Thomas Hart Benton over a plan proposed by a \u201cCommittee of Thirteen.\u201d Charles Jenkins\u2019 Georgia Platform promised \u201cno further assaults\u201d on rights as long as this agreement was in place. The boundaries of Texas were set by this agreement in exchange for the assumption of $10 million of debt. Trading slaves in Washington D.C. was made illegal by, for ten points, what series of five bills negotiated by Henry Clay that eased tensions between slave and free states?", "answer": "<b> Compromise</b> of<b> 1850</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "The goals of this period were changed in the \u201cReverse Course\u201d which instead aimed to create a strong industrial base. The Recreation and Amusement Association was created during this period to oversee legalized prostitution and reduce the incidents of rape. This period was ended by the San Francisco Peace Treaty which restored sovereignty to a certain nation except for the Ryukyu Islands. The MacArthur Constitution was drafted during, for ten points, what post-World War II period in which an East Asian nation was occupied by the United States?", "answer": "<b> occupation of Japan</b> (accept<b> Japan</b> after occupation is read; prompt on \u201cpost-war Japan\u201d)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "In 2004, Jacques Chirac ordered the destruction of this country\u2019s air force after 9 French peacekeepers were killed in Bouak\u00b4e. The Linas-Marcoussis Agreement failed to end a civil war in this country which began after the RDR\u2019s candidate was disqualified by the FPI\u2019s leader. Henri Konan B\u00b4edi\u00b4e ruled this country after the death of its longtime first president Felix Houphou\u00a8et-Boigny. Laurent Gbagbo led, for ten points, what West African country home to Yamoussoukro and Abidjan?", "answer": "<b> Ivory Coast</b> (Accept<b> Cote D\u2019Ivoire</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "A reference to one painting of this person in Natsume Soseki\u2019s<em> Grass Pillow</em> popularized that painting in Japan. Salvador Dali made a 1973 etching of this person in response to that painting, which also may have influenced a John Waterhouse painting of this person in a white and gold dress putting red poppies in her hair. This person\u2019s dress temporarily keeps her afloat in one painting based on a scene related by Queen Gertrude. John Everett Millais painted, for ten points, what character from<em> Hamlet</em> as she drowns.", "answer": "<b> Ophelia</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "This man\u2019s father was taken hostage by a group of students including Samuel L. Jackson during his father\u2019s term as trustee for Morehouse College. Marcus Wayne Chenault stated \u201call Christians are my enemies\u201d after killing this man\u2019s mother in 1974. In this man\u2019s final speech, he spoke of \u201cpublic servants, who happen to be sanitation workers.\u201d This man\u2019s wife was nearly killed by a bomb in 1956 which targeted their Montgomery home. For ten points, name this Civil Rights leader who was assassinated in 1968 by James Earl Ray.", "answer": "Martin Luther<b> King</b> Jr. (accept<b> MLK</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "For 10 points, name this Sunni fundamentalist group whose control over Afghanistan was the target of 2001\u2019s Operation Enduring Freedom.", "answer": "The<b> Taliban</b> [accept<b> Islamic Emirate of Afghanistan</b>,<b> IEA</b>]", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "The Duke of Buckingham failed to relieve the siege of one city affected by this law. Cardinal Richelieu\u2019s siege of La Rochelle ended that city\u2019s status as a military \u201csafe haven\u201d designated by two letters patent accompanying this law. The subjects of this law were given refuge by the Edict of Potsdam after this law was revoked by Louis XIV in the Edict of Fontainebleau. For ten points, name this law promulgated by Henry IV which granted some tolerance to Huguenots in France.", "answer": "Edict of<b> Nantes</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "At one of these locations, Mario Savio urged listeners to \u201cput your bodies upon the gears.\u201d Roslyn Pope drafted \u201cAn Appeal for Human Rights\u201d in the aftermath of a series of 1960 protests at one of these locations. John Filo won a Pulitzer for a picture taken at one of these institutions showing a Mary Ann Vecchio kneeling over the body of Jeffery Miller. Marshall Sahlins, in protest of the Vietnam War, developed the concept of a \u201cteach-in\u201d at one of these institutions in Ann Arbor. For ten points, name these institutions of higher education.", "answer": "<b> universities</b> (accept<b> college</b>s; prompt on schools; prompt on campuses)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This assembly represented all of Russia\u2019s feudal class, including the nobles, the clergy, and the commoners.", "answer": "<b> Zemsky Sobor</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The uncle of this man was killed and had his liver taken as a prize at the Battle of Uhud. In the Story of the Cranes, this person was said to have initially accepted the idols Lat, Manat, and Uzza. This person fled one city on the horse Buraq, and was married to Aisha. Jibreel aided this person during the Battle of Badr, and during the Night Journey, this person lowered the required number of prayers from 50 to 5 per day. For ten points, name this man, the final prophet and founder of Islam.", "answer": "<b> Muhammad</b>", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {}, {"question": "<b>Description acceptable. Legal authorities began their policy of not disclosing victims\u2019names after Maria Elena learned about this event from watching television. Waylon Jennings and Tommy Allsup continued the (+) \u201cWinter Dance Party\u201d tour despite this event, which Allsup allegedly avoided by losing a coin toss, a story depicted in the film</b><em><b> La Bamba</b></em><b>. This event is presumed to be the (*)</b> \u201cbad news on the doorstep\u201d in Don McLean\u2019s \u201cAmerican Pie.\u201d For ten points, name this event that resulted in the deaths of J.P. Richardson, Ritchie Valens, and the lead singer of The Crickets.", "answer": "The<b> Day the Music Died</b> (accept answers describing the<b> plane Crash</b> that killed Buddy <b>Holly</b>; accept equivalent for plane crash)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "<b>This country\u2019s Red Week strikes were supported by the PSI, whose own members were split into the Reformist and Maximalist factions. Troops belonging to this country were</b> <b>massacred in (+)</b> <b>Tripoli by the Ottomans, and this country entered a war after being</b> <b>promised South Tyrol in the Treaty of London. Failed negotiations over (*)</b> Fiume prompted this country\u2019s Prime Minister Vittorio Orlando to quit the Paris Peace Conference prematurely. A retreat from Caporetto was a disaster for, for ten points, what country whose king Victor Emmanuel III joined the Allies in WWI in 1915?", "answer": "Kingdom of<b> Italy</b> (do not accept \u201cRepublic of Italy\u201d)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>The first entry on the QV catalog contains around 200 works for this instrument. Paul Taffanel was the dedicatee of a D major concertino for this instrument by Cecile Chaminade, while Johann Joachim (+) Quantz was a prolific composer for it. A work this instrument is named for a property of platinum,</b><em><b> Density 21.5</b></em><b>, and is by Edgard Var`ese. This instrument plays a chromatic descent to open (*)</b> Debussy\u2019s<em> Prelude to the Afternoon of a Faun</em>. Frederick the Great was a virtuoso of, for ten points, what transverse woodwind instrument, a larger relative of the piccolo?", "answer": "<b> flute</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b>Robert Bellah used a quote from this book to title his</b><em><b> Habits of the Heart</b></em><b>. Louis Hartz opened</b><em><b> The Liberal Tradition in America</b></em><b> with a quote from this book about a country</b> <b>where people are (+)</b> <b>\u201cborn equal\u201d rather than \u201cbecoming equal.\u201d In a section titled for</b> <b>the \u201cThree Races\u201d of its title country, this book predicts a race war between blacks and (*) </b> whites. The author of this book traveled with Gustave de Beaumont in 1831 to investigate the title country\u2019s prison system. For ten points, name this book written by Alexis de Tocqueville about the political system of the United States.", "answer": "On<b> Democracy in America</b> (accept De La<b> Democratie en Amerique</b>)", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Other Social Science"}, {}, {"question": "<b>James Seagrove helped one revolutionary from this country escape to the United States where he met Susan Livingston. That man from this country earned the temporary rank of</b> <b>lieutenant colonel while attacking Fort Pensacola and was later arrested by (+)</b> <b>Bernardo</b> <b>de G\u00b4alvez for invading the Bahamas. Another revolutionary from this country revived a republic in this country after issuing the (*)</b> Cartagena Manifesto and conducting the Admirable Campaign. Francisco de Miranda was a sometimes ally of Sim\u00b4on Bol\u00b4\u0131var in fighting for the independence of, for ten points, what country?", "answer": "<b> Venezuela</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>R. R. Palmer pioneered the historiography of this body of water in a work that advanced the comparative approach to studying this body of water. That book blamed shared political</b> <b>(+)</b> <b>troubles and ideas across this body of water for its titular events and was called</b><em><b> The</b></em> <em><b>Age of Democratic Revolutions</b></em><b>. One economic model of this body of water includes the export of (*)</b> tobacco and sugar produced by imported slaves in Caribbean colonies. The Triangle Trade occurred on, for ten points, what body of water which separated Europe from its empires in Africa and the Americas?", "answer": "The<b> Atlantic</b> Ocean", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "<b>According to one story, a general who refused orders to kill this ruler in his infancy was secretly fed his own son in retribution. That general, Harpagus, later defected to this man during a revolt against (+) Astyages. This man won the Battle of Thymbra against Croesus of Lydia, and he was later killed by the Massagetae queen (*)</b> Tomyris. This ruler was succeeded by his son Cambyses II and issued a statement of tolerance on a namesake cylinder. For the point, name this founder of the Achaemenid Empire, the first Persian Empire.", "answer": "<b> Cyrus the Great</b> (accept<b> Cyrus II</b>)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}